Guide to Congregation Kether Torah, Pittsburgh, Pa. Historical Miscellanea, 1914-1958 AIS.1988.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Congregation Kether Torah, Pittsburgh, Pa. Historical Miscellanea
1914-1958
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Congregation Kether Torah (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1988.04
0.56 Linear Feet
This collection contains miscellaneous records of Congregation Kether Torah (Pittsburgh, Pa.), including: history, charter, by-laws, membership lists from c. 1960, minutes of eight congregational meetings between 1927 and 1939, papers concerning the sale of the synagogue property in the Hill District, blueprint and legal documents concerning cemetery in Reserve Township, Pa., some general correspondence and a blueprint of synagogue from c. 1913.
History
This synagogue, originally named Kaiser Torah, was founded at the corner of Webster Avenue and Erin Street in the Hill District, Pittsburgh, Pa. In 1922, it changed its name to Congregation Kether Torah, and later, in the 1950s, moved to Bartlett Street in Squirrel Hill, Pittsburgh, Pa.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains miscellaneous records including: history, charter, by-laws, membership lists from c. 1960, minutes of eight congregational meetings between 1927 and 1939, papers concerning the sale of the synagogue property in the Hill District, blueprint and legal documents concerning cemetery in Reserve Township, Pa., some general correspondence and a blueprint of synagogue from c. 1913.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. Richard Linder in May 1988.
Previous Citation
Congregation Kether Torah, Pittsburgh, Pa. Historical Miscellanea, 1914-1958, AIS.1988.04, Archives Services Center, University of Pittsburgh
Churches and Synagogues; Cemeteries -- Pennsylvania -- Reserve; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Synagogues -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Judaism -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Congregation Kether Torah (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Congregation Kaiser Torah (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- History, I.
  - History material, 1910-1935, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Content Notes
    Includes: Congregation Keser Torah, Pittsburgh, PA: Silver Anniversary 1910-1935
    Invitation to 68th Anniversary Celebration, June 8, 1975
    "Kether Torah Observes 68th," Jewish Chronicle of Pittsburgh, May 8, 1975
    Photograph of "68 Years Old," Jewish Chronicle of Pittsburgh, May 22, 1975
- Charter, II.
  - Orginal Charter and Amendments, 1914 and 1923 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes: Orginal Charter, September 5, 1914
    Amendments to Charter, July 1923
    The name change from Congregation Kaiser Torah to Congregation Kether Torah.
- By-laws, III.
  - By-laws and copies (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes: Copies in Hebrew
- Membership, IV.
  - Membership lists (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes: Three lists giving names, addresses of synagogue members; two lists are undated and the third has "circa 1960" written across it.
  - Minutes of Members Congregation Meetings (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes: Minutes all written in Hebrew.
    Meeting minutes, January 20, 1927
    Meeting minutes, February 20, 1927
    Meeting minutes, January 7, 1929
    Meeting minutes, February 9, 1935
    Meeting minutes, February 23, 1935
    Meeting minutes, December 10, 1938
    Meeting minutes, January 7, 1939
    Meeting minutes, January 16, 1939
    Notice of special meeting May 2, 1951 (in English)
- Sale of Synagogue Property to Carter Chapel Colored Methodist Church of Pittsburgh, Pa., 1951-1952; V.
  - Schedule of payments and Agreement of sale/indenture, with drafts (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Legal Papers, VI.
  - Congregation Kether Torah v. Jacob Gordon, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes: Leases, court documents, and correspondence dealing with the eviction of Jacob Gordon from congregation-owned property.
  - Land claim, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes: Court documents reasserting that the sale of land on Erin St. in Pittsburgh to the Congregation was legal and valid.
  - Leases, 1926, 1946, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes: Leases and related correspondence for dwelling on cemetery property.
- Cemetery (Reserve Township), VII.
  - Land purchase, 1916, 1943-1944, 1946, 1949, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes: Correspondence and legal documents involving the purchase of the cemetery grounds from the estate of Joseph H. Heil.
  - Cemetery Blueprints, Deeds, and Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes: a Blueprint, 1946
    Deeds, 1914, 1949
    Copies of deeds and agreements for cemetery lots, 1914, 1949
    Cemetery rules, undated
    Cemetery related correspondence, 1949-1952
- General Correspondence, 1920-1952; VIII.
  - General Correspondence, 1920-1924, 1940, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Finances, IX.
  - Building fund and contributions (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes: Build fund material
    Contributors list giving names and amounts of gift
    "An Urgent Appeal to the Jewish Public," Jewish Criterion, undated
    Two ads for contributions from Jewish Criterion, undated
    Blank contribution form
  - Gemilut Hesed (Free Loan Association) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Taxes--Application for exemption, and correspondence, 1937, 1947-1950 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mortgages (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes: Legal documents of Congregation's mortgages
    Documents mortgages to: Washington Trust Company, August Hoffman; Colonial Trust Company, South Side Trust Company of Pittsburg,; Carl and John Ehrlinger, Fifth Avenue Bank of Pittsburgh, and Merchants Savings and Trust Company
    List of bond holders and their debts, 1921-1949
  - Financial correspondence, 1922-1925, 1937, 1941, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Blueprint of Synagogue, 1913; X.
  - Blueprint of Synagogue, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 19)